YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series IV. Constituent Groups
Sophia Smith Collection
By the 1930s some white women in the YWCA came to understand that some of the problems African-Americans faced, such as lynching and other forms of racial violence, would not be solved through education alone. The death of a much-loved and highly respected former national staff member, Juliette Derricotte, in 1931 as a result of receiving sub-standard medical care after a car accident in segregated Georgia, increased the sense of urgency about refocusing the Association's efforts to address race problems.
As the National Association moved into more active "interracial" (as opposed to separate "Colored") work, civil rights issues were added to the Public Affairs Program. The Program for 1932-34 included "Study and support of measures for enlarged economic opportunities for the Negro race" and "Local YWCA efforts to foster right public opinion which shall be effective in dealing with the menace of lynching and mob violence in every form." "Convention Bulletin Number V-Looking Toward a National Public Affairs Program for 1934-36" includes a section called "Our Responsibility in Regard to Special Problems of Minority Groups." Describing the relations of white and Black people in America as "crucial for the future welfare of both races and for the progress of our democratic institutions," it reads in part, "[p]roposals for different standards... which will place Negroes on a lower or segregated status should be opposed." Interracial cooperation, and equal treatment and opportunities for all people continued as major Public Affairs themes for the rest of the century.
The staff reorganization and reduction of 1931-32 eliminated many of the specialist staff positions and moved some from direct advisory service to Community Associations into an educational role. It also eliminated the Council of Colored Work. With this reorganization came the beginnings of a shift in terminology from "Colored" Work to "Interracial" Work. Eva Bowles, moved from the Field Division to the Laboratory Division, initially praised the new staff allocation as "a real achievement in interracial set-up," but Bowles' niece later wrote that her aunt felt the reorganization would diminish "participation of Negroes in the policy making" of the Association ("Eva Bowles" by Clarice Winn Davis in the Dictionary of American Negro Biography). Bowles resigned in the spring of 1932.
As the YWCA of the USA moved out of its initial period of expansion, it felt the need of a device for measuring the quality of its Associations' programs. The Standards Study (1935-39) defined a set of "principles by which Associations may be recognized as members of the National Association in good standing or sub-standard." Part Two of the Study, "The Branch Study," presented at Convention in 1938, looked at the "particularly difficult administrative and structural problem" of the metropolitan Association with one or more branches. Some city Associations had developed policies which excluded members of "Negro" branches from "electoral membership" in the Central Association, claiming that status as "branch electors," with a say only in branch activities, qualified as "electoral membership," a basic element of membership in the National Association.
Pointing up the inherent injustice of such policies, the Branch Study presented the issue in stark terms: "If a local Association should write into its constitution that electorship was open only to 'white' women and girls, that Association would automatically be disaffiliated from the national organization." Noting that "the growing self-consciousness of the racial branches has made this problem more apparent," the Branch Study went on to state in unequivocal terms that the practice by some Associations, of excluding Black members from electoral membership in the Association "violates the Constitutional integrity of the Associations concerned."
The 1940 Convention authorized a Commission to Study Interracial Practices in Community YWCAs, which recommended "that the implications of the YWCA Purpose be recognized as involving the inclusion of Negro women and girls in the main stream of Association life, and that such inclusion be adopted as a conscious goal." The Commission's final report, Interracial Practices in Community YWCAs, was issued in 1944 with a set of recommendations. After two years of follow up, the 1946 National Convention adopted the Interracial Charter, which not only pledged to work towards an interracial experience within the YW, but also to fight against injustice on the basis of race, "whether in the community, the nation or the world."
Despite this declaration of intent, progress, particularly at the local level, was not especially brisk. At the Convention following the Brown v. Board of Education Supreme Court decision in 1954, the National Association returned to the issue of the racial segregation in the Association. Various Committees, Advisory Groups, and Work Groups reviewed the Association's progress. The Interdepartmental Committee to Coordinate Work on Racial Integration (1957-58), a special committee preparing material for the 1958 Convention Workbook, recommended formation of the Committee on Racial Inclusiveness to assure that Convention actions on Racial Inclusiveness were interpreted and carried out in every part of Association life.
With the increasing momentum of the Civil Rights movement, the YWCA's public advocacy activities increased. The National Student Council was particularly active in sit-ins and protests.
At its meeting in June of 1963 the National Board allocated funds to launch a country-wide Action Program for Integration and Desegregation of Community YWCAs. Dorothy Height took leave from her position as Associate Director for Training to head the program. With passage of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 "the practices implied in our Interracial Charter" became law.
At the end of the two-year Action Program in 1965, the National Board adopted a proposal to accelerate the work "in going beyond token integration and making a bold assault on all aspects of racial segregation." It set aside $200,000 to support the effort, establishing the Office of Racial Integration (re-named Office of Racial Justice in 1969) as part of the Executive Office. In her role as its first Director, Dorothy Height helped to monitor the Association's progress toward full integration, kept abreast of the civil rights movement, facilitated "honest dialogue," aided in making best use of African-American leadership (both volunteer and staff), and helped in their recruitment and retention.
Nearly thirty years after the Branch Study Report of 1938 had brought the constitutional implications of segregated Association practices to the attention of the National Association, some Associations continued to resist meaningful integration. Hoping that persuasion and education would ultimately prevail, the National Association also moved in 1967 to amend the YWCA Constitution so as to make full integration of Community Associations a condition for continued affiliation with the National Association. The Office of Racial Justice sponsored the Dialogue Program in 1967-68 in which Community and Student YWCAs held dialogue group workshops. In the following year Racial Justice Institutes were led by National Board members and staff all over the country to bring greater awareness to local YWCAs of race relations in the United States and to provide resources to encourage black economic and community development.
Administrative History
1907/8- Special Workers in Student Department
1913- Secretaries for Colored Work; Colored Work, Cities; and Colored Schools in Method Department
1916 Secretaries for Colored Work, Cities; and Colored Schools in Method Department
1917 Secretary for Colored Work, Cities; Special Worker, Colored; in Department of Method; Special Workers for War Work Council
1918-19 Secretary for Colored Work, Cities; Special Worker, Colored Schools; Colored Work, Industrial; and Special War Work in Department of Method; Special Workers for War Work Council
1920 Secretaries for Colored Work, Cities; Girls' Work, Colored; and Colored Work, Student in Department of Research and Method; Secretaries for Student Colored Work in Field Work Department; Special Workers in Continuation Committee staff
1921-22 Secretaries for Colored Work, Cities; and Girls' Work, Colored in Research and Method Department and Secretaries for Colored Work, Student; and Colored Work, Cities in Field Work Department; and Industrial, Colored on Post-Continuation Committee staff.
1923-24 Secretaries in City Department, Student Department, and Girl Reserve Department of the Field Division
1925-26 Administrator in City Department, and Secretary in the Girl Reserve Department of the Field Division and Administrator in the National Student Council
1927-30 Administrators of Colored Work in the City Department of the Field Division and in the National Student Council
1932-39 staff for Colored Work and Interracial Relations/Education in National Services Division and Program staff in Laboratory Division
1940-49 Program staff in Community Division
1965-71 Office of Racial Integration/Racial Justice (name change 1969)
Scope and Content-Part 2. "Colored," and "Interracial," Work, 1906-70
Records related to "Colored" and "Interracial" work consist of general historical materials; committee minutes; files on related activities in various YWCA departments; files on policies and practices of Community Associations; records of YWCA and National Conferences, Consultations and Workshops; records of relations with a few related organizations; programs and projects files; publications; reference files; reports; studies; and training materials.
The records in this section largely consist of materials gathered together under "Interracial" in the National Association's central Subject File and focus almost entirely on relationships between Black and white women. These items were compiled from various department and committee records to provide YWCA staff with useful information about the subject. While they provide a serviceable introduction to the work, there is much material elsewhere in the records, particularly in the various departments in which the "colored" secretaries served. In fact, the central nature of this difficult struggle in YWCA history means that there is almost no portion of the records where the topic is entirely absent.
Included are selected reports, memoranda, and other general materials about "Colored" and "Interracial" work in various YWCA departments. The Public Affairs files are especially extensive. Administrative responsibility for racial justice activities was more centralized after establishment of the Office of Racial Integration in 1965, and especially after the One Imperative Convention in 1970. [see "Racial Justice" work below]
Over the years YWCA staff compiled information for its central Subject Files on African-American staff members, actions taken at Convention involving the constituency and racial justice issues, and YWCA policies and statements about the work and about YWCA-owned properties. There is also extensive historical research on the "Colored" Work in the YWCA, 1907-20 by Jane Olcott Waters.
Self-studies, dated between 1919 and 1959 and primarily about "racial inclusiveness" policies in Community Associations, indicate both the YWCA's dogged efforts to achieve meaningful integration within the Association, and the slow pace of progress. The Studies perhaps demonstrate most clearly the difficulties of being a national membership-directed organization in a country with such widely divergent attitudes.
Publications include pamphlets, books, study outlines, program materials, and serials. There are publications about YWCA work with African-American women and about YWCA policies and practices; a history of the Work of Colored Women during World War I; and techniques for improving race relations, including program suggestions and educational materials.
The "Interracial" records also contain files on racist incidents involving YWCA staff and the National Association's response. These include correspondence and other materials about the death of Juliette Derricotte.
The Minutes and Reports filed here are of the Committees with primary responsibility for "Colored" work, interracial education, and racial justice policies, 1917-70. The Reports include some of the regular secretarial reports written by African-American staff members (others can be found in the records of their Department or Committee in other Record Groups), some miscellaneous reports, and three 1950s reports on racial inclusiveness and combating racism.
Conference files include reports, brochures, and local arrangements materials related to YWCA "Colored" and Branch Conferences, and other YWCA Conferences and workshops for training and interracial dialogue. There are also files on a few national non-YWCA conferences on race relations and civil rights.
The bulk of the Project files are related to the Action Program, Project Equality, and the Dialogue Program from the 1960s.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The "Interracial" records and Minutes and Reports on the microfilm were not discarded after filming, so most of the microfilmed records can also be consulted in original format.
The Local Associations files include records of interactions between "Colored" Branches (often named Phyllis Wheatley Branch) and the National Association. They appear on the microfilm (along with other types of branches and International Institutes) following the general records for that Association. For example, under North Carolina, general records about the Charlotte Association appear on reel 199 at microdex 3. These are followed by "Charlotte-Phyllis Wheatley Branch.") These records were discarded after filming, so are only available on microfilm.
Records can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Colored Work [includes Colored Work Council and other groups as well as "History of Colored Work, 1907-20" compiled by Jane Olcott Waters]
Racial Justice Committee
Race Relations Committee
Subject Files
Interracial
Fields and Field Work, Policy, Colored Work 1921
Local Associations
Usually under Phyllis Wheatley Branch, filed alphabetically by state and then City/Name of the Association
Original Format Records, 1907-2002, n.d., 18 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
The records in this section are arranged in the following units
General and History
Committees
Departments, Divisions, and Offices
Community Associations
Conventions, Conferences, and Consultations
Organizations
Programs and Projects
Publications
Reference materials
Reports
Studies
Training
PART 3. "RACIAL JUSTICE" WORK, 1970-2001
Historical Note
Just prior to the 1970 Convention, 500 Black women came together for a National Conference of Black Women in the YWCA. Their report to the full YWCA membership at Convention said in part:
"We are solidly united in determination to close the gap between the YWCA ideals as stated in the purpose and YWCA practices. We will no longer tolerate false liberalism... Recognizing that the YWCA cannot be all things to all people, we demand that it put its full force behind one issue inherent in all of the imperatives stated in the 1970 Convention Work Book. That imperative is the elimination of racism wherever it exists and by any means necessary."
After intense discussion, the Convention delegates voted to adopt "The One Imperative."
Following Convention, the Office of Racial Justice sponsored a series of workshops, institutes, consultations, and meetings as part of the One Imperative Program. Various groups of YWCA women-Asian-American, Native-American, Puerto Rican, white, black, and others--attended consultations. In the course of this process, the YWCA's goal of "integration and desegregation" was recharacterized as a racial and social justice agenda. What had been defined by the Association as essentially a white and black issue, now encompassed all ethnic groups.
The One Imperative Program also included the Action Audit for Change, a process by which Community and Student Associations audited their progress on racial justice issues including policies and programs. The National Board went through a similar process in the later 1970s. As of the 1976 Convention, regular Action Audits were made part of the periodic comprehensive review of Associations that were required for continuing affiliation with the National Association.
In the 1990s Racial Justice staff worked to document and distribute successful racial justice and diversity initiatives; develop racial justice program resources and provide training; work with associations to develop strategies to eliminate institutional racism in education, law enforcement, housing, health care, and financial institutions at local, state and national level; and plan two public awareness events, the National Day of Commitment to Eliminate Racism, and the YWCA Week Without Violence. By adding "Human Rights," to the name of the office in 1997, the Association officially extended its work to fight oppression of all groups, not just those based upon race or ethnicity.
Administrative History
1969-71 Office of Racial Justice
1972-c.1983 Center for Racial Justice under Program and Development Unit
1984-91 Assistant to Executive Director for Racial Justice in Executive Office
Sep 1992- Racial Justice Center
1997- Office of Racial Justice and Human Rights
Scope and Content-Part 3. "Racial Justice" Work, 1970-2002
Records related to "Racial Justice" Work consist of general historical materials; committee records; Racial Justice Center and Office files; general and reference files on American Indian and Mexican-American women; information about racial justice programs at Community and Student Associations; Conference files; program files; information about a few public advocacy activities; publications; and training materials.
Though the records reflect the expanded Racial Justice agenda, which included all women of color and eventually all oppressed groups, but the bulk of the records deal with black and white relations.
As is the case elsewhere in the records, very few records have survived from between 1970 and 1988.
The records document the intense activity following the National Convention in 1970 and its associated institutes, consultations, meetings, and workshops, as well as the continuing One Imperative Program. Conference files include planning materials and reports from conferences and consultations with black, white, Native American, Asian-American, and Puerto Rican women in the YWCA. One Imperative Program files include records about the development of the Action Audit for Change self-study process for Community and Student YWCAs. The 1970s also saw a flurry of new Racial Justice publications.
Records from the 1990s and up to 2001 indicate a similar concentration of activity.
There are files on the Racial Justice [and Human Rights] Office's responses to renewed Ku Klux Klan activity and hate crimes against homosexuals in late 1990s as well records of the Racial Justice Convocation in 1990 to develop a Racial Justice agenda for the Twenty-first century and a follow-up Conference in 1999. There are also planning materials, correspondence, and other records related to the public awareness campaigns of the late 1990s, including the National Day of Commitment to Eliminate Racism and its associated Stop Racism Youth Challenge and Race Against Racism; as well as Statewide Days of Dialogue on Race Relations in 1998.
1990s records of training activities include the Mission Empowerment process, stressing the One Imperative, and the Racial Justice Training Manual, 1996.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
The records that were microfilmed date through 1970 only, so there is little on the microfilm related to the Racial Justice Work. What is there can be found in the Subject Files under Convention 1970 and Interracial.
Original Format Records, 1907-2002, n.d., 18 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
The records in this section are arranged in the following units
General and History
Committees
Offices
American Indian Women
Community and Student Associations
Conferences, Consultations, and Convocations
Mexican-American Women
Programs
Public Advocacy
Publications
Training
Related Materials
Elsewhere in this Series
Race issues were so central to Association activities that there is related material in the conference records, publications, and program materials in the files of every constituent group.
Subseries A. Employed Women includes information about African-American women in Industry and "Household Employment."
Subseries B. Immigration and Foreign Communities Up until 1970, work on behalf of Asian-Americans, Mexican-Americans and other groups was considered part of the Immigration work.
Subseries D. Teen-Age and Younger Girls includes extensive records of segregated Teen conferences on microfilm.
Elsewhere in this Record Group
Microfilmed records of the National Association of Professional Workers in SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL includes a study on the status of "Negro" workers in the YWCA, 1944-45.
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY has extensive files on the YWCA's civil rights efforts.
SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS contains publications and scripts in the Music, and Pageantry and Drama subseries reflecting the National staff's experimentation with many different techniques for presenting concepts.
The YWCA's main serial the Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS contains many articles related to race issues.
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES has records related to the greatly expanded "Colored" Work during World War I, and the Japanese Evacuee Project during World War II.
In other Record Groups
Materials relating to race relations and racial justice can be found throughout the records, especially in the following:
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE, SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION under Racial Justice has correspondence related to Civil Rights activities dating from the late-1950s through the mid-1960s.
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES has records of resolutions and actions, plus reports of major studies presented to the membership at Convention. Proceedings often include extensive transcriptions of discussions and debate at Convention.
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK Since the first African-American national staff members were employees in the Student Department, the earliest records about the work can be found in this Record Group. Through the years, the Students often advocated the more radical positions in the Association. They were active in the Civil Rights Movement and in other racial justice activities and participated in a number of "human relations" summer projects in the 1960s.
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS Local Associations files on the Microfilm contain some records of interactions with various kinds of Branches including "Colored" or "Negro" and Japanese Branches. There are also community studies on interracial relations and studies and reports on work with Mexican women. Original format Community Associations files contain some Action Reports completed as part of the accreditation process.
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS contains footage of 1990s Convocations, conferences, and meetings, as well as a variety of educational video presentations about racial justice issues.
Elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection: